Finding Aid for the Arthur Stern papers, 1938-2013 LSC.2332
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 3: Personal materials, 1940-2012
  - Correspondence: family and friends, 1951-1971 (Box 49, Folders 4-6)
    German materials include: Correspondence from Robert Stern regarding visits, Jewish holidays, and brief career updates. Correspondence from Prof. M. Strutt in Zurich about Arthur’s work in electrical engineering/with transistors, thanking him for scientific help and input, the births of Daniel and Claude Stern and from Prof. Weber regarding students interested in transistors. Updates from family in England, letters from unknown person in Zurich regarding career changes, construction in Zurich. Letters from Irene Michel in Zurich to Edith regarding the birth of Danny Stern, their (Irene and Louis’) engagement and increased Jewish orthodoxy, her health, asking advice on relationship problems (prior to meeting Louis), work considerations at Butonia, reply from Edith to Irene regarding her pregnancy with Danny, the differences between Switzerland and the USA, their record collection, and their new house. Letter from Edith to George Mezoefi regarding her first months in the US, reply from George about work at MGM (Ivanhoe, Singin’ in the Rain, etc.), 3D films in Switzerland and other work updates. Letters from various family members and friends with brief life and health updates, and discussions of their children (particularly Danny’s birth). Arthur Stern’s employment contract as an assistant at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich, Correspondence between Josef Stern and Simon Wiesenthal regarding licenses in Austria, business and legal correspondence from Leon Stern, personal correspondence between Bertha Stern and family providing general updates, family correspondence between Edith and her parents regarding travel and health updates, as well as with Stern’s parents on same subjects.
  - Correspondence: postwar, Edith and Arthur, Edith and family, 1945-1951 (Box 49, Folder 7)
    German materials include: Correspondence from Edith to Arthur about his experiences in and impressions of the USA (including anti-Semitism), career plans, travels, necessary visa paperwork and other visa related issues, her stress regarding work, films and social life, health updates (particularly regarding an operation on her legs), preparations for Jewish holidays, current events (threats of war, Swiss newspapers,. Correspondence from Edith’s mother and sister to Arthur about travels, Arthur’s experiences in the US, Edith’s visa application process. Telegram to Arthur from his Grandparents on his 20th birthday.
  - Holocaust artifacts, 1933, 1944-1947 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    German materials include: Leon Stern's ID card from during German occupation of Budapest stating his profession and role in collecting clothing, Leon Stern's immunization card as member of the Central Council of Jews in Budapest 1944, permit from Central Council for him to monitor food supply in hospitals and detention camps, receipt from application for Stern family emigration to Palestine, note thanking Leon for assisting with French-speaking refugees after the war.
  - Congratulatory telegrams: Arthur and Edith Wedding, 1952 (Box 50, Folders 2-3)
    Cards, telegrams, letters and a poem from friends and family congratulating Arthur and Edith Stern on their marriage, letters to Leon Stern congratulating him on his son’s marriage.
  - Leon and Bertha Stern: Correspondence, refugee and immigration documents, and death certificates, 1938, 1947-1954, 1985-1986 (Box 50, Folder 4)
    German materials include: Correspondence with Leo Pugatsch regarding order for various chemicals, letter from Budapest regarding experiences in the Hungarian revolution 1956 comparing it to experiences during WW2. Letter from Josef Stern to family August 1945 regarding finding who survived and his experience in Auschwitz and other Concentration Camps during the war. Correspondence from Swiss authorities regarding finding family after the war. Letter to Arthur written in event of Leon Stern’s death during surgery regarding his financial assets. Letter to Josef Stern and testament of Leon Stern outlining financial assets.
    French materials include: official Swiss documents related to liberation and permission to travel.
  - Family correspondence and immigration documents, 1970-1981 (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Mother's estate, 1983-1997 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    German materials include: tax documents and asset inventory and summary for Hulda Samuel-Besser (Edith’s mother) after her death in January 1983, financial documents, invoices and documents pertaining to inheritance and division of assets between heirs, correspondence with manager of Hulda Samuel-Besser’s property in Zurich, appraisal of her valuables, correspondence regarding memorial and gravestone, pamphlets from the Union Bank of Switzerland on taxes and inheritance laws and regulations, Hulda Samuel-Besser’s death certificate, obituary in Zurich’s daily newspaper.
  - Leon Stern speeches ("Papa's Speeches"), 1962-1966 (Box 51, Folder 1)
    Speech given by Danny(?) at Bar Mitzvah thanking his parents and acknowledging his new role as a Jewish adult, speeches by Leon Stern on the Bar Mitzvah of Danny Stern and Marcell Stern on biblical and Jewish themes of adulthood and celebration.
  - Geneva pending matters, 1969-1982 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    German materials include: Report on Swiss buyer fees, report regarding dividends from British war loans, notes regarding creation and demand for payment for a memorial plaque for Stern’s parents.
    French materials include: Correspondence regarding Swiss bank accounts.
  - Leon and Bertha Stern inheritance - inactive, 1982, 1986-1987 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    German materials include: Official pamphlets from Swiss association of lawyers regarding regulations of their fees and associated responsibilities.
    French materials include: Inventory of Swiss bank safe deposit box.
  - Leon and Bertha Stern: will, death certificates, and correspondence, 1982-1997 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    German materials include: doctor’s report on the health of Bertha Stern, two letters from Bertha Stern to Claude and Jackie Stern about travels, university, and summer break, paperwork and statements regarding the healthcare of Leon and Bertha Stern, correspondence related to parents' stay in Vevey, and Leon Stern’s will.
    French Materials include: death certificates for Leon and Bertha Stern and related medical correspondence from nursing home, letters thanking Arthur Stern for donations in his father’s name, correspondence from nursing home regarding parents’ room and finances, announcement of Leon Stern’s death.
  - Leon and Bertha Stern: obituaries, 1985-1986 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    Obituary for Leon Stern detailing his personal and work history, obituary for Bertha Stern detailing her past and relationship to Leon, as well as an article commemorating the unveiling of their shared gravestone and providing a detailed personal history of Leon and Bertha.
  - Leon and Bertha Stern: mausoleum, 1986 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    German materials include: Document written by Stern giving short biography of his parents in honor of the unveiling of their gravestone in Geneva.
    French materials include: Correspondence from Robert to gravestone vendor regarding sketches for mausoleum.
  - Correspondence: condolences, 1986 (Box 51, Folders 7-8)
    Condolence letters and correspondence on the occasion of Stern’s father and mother’s deaths.
  - Correspondence: gravestone in Veyrier, 2007-2009 (Box 51, Folder 9)
    French materials include: correspondence to Robert regarding parent’s gravestone in Veyrier.
  - Correspondence: from and related to Leon and Bertha Stern, 1967, 1983 (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Arthur, Edith, and friends, 1974-1975 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    German materials include: Correspondence from friends regarding their health, thank-you's for bar mitzvah gifts, greeting for the Jewish High holidays.
    French materials include: thank you note from a friend.
  - Correspondence: Robert Stern and family, 1976-1997 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Arthur and Robert Stern, 1982, 1986 (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Stern family - children and grandchildren, 1971-2011 (Box 52, Folders 5-7)
  - Correspondence: Stern family, 1973-2008 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    German material includes: Letter from family in Switzerland with good wishes for Jewish New Year and general updates.
  - Family correspondence and history, 1988-2008 (Box 52, Folders 9-10)
    German materials include: Memorial notice for yearly remembrance of the death of Leon Stern and Hulda Samuel-Besser, first letter from Arthur to uncle Josef Stern after the war regarding who made it through the war, his experiences arriving in Switzerland and the struggles (particularly financial) of life as a refugee, assets remaining in Hungary, possible return to Hungary and related challenges.
  - Correspondence and ephemera, 1979-1984 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Saved articles and related correspondence, 1985, 2007-2011 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - Personal correspondence: philanthropy and estate matters, 1989 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - Personal communication: Jewish politics, 2002-2003, 2011 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: first transistor radio, 2003-2012 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Personal correspondence, 1969-2011 (Box 53, Folders 6-8, Box 54, Folders 1-5)
    German materials include: correspondence with relatives in Europe, primarily good wishes and short family updates around the Jewish High Holidays, thank you cards and good wishes for the Jewish High Holidays, brief correspondence regarding real estate in Berlin and with relatives in Europe regarding general life updates, cards of congratulations and good wishes, casual correspondence with and cards and thank you notes from family in Europe, thank you note, gift of a tree in honor of birthday, correspondence with friends and family in Switzerland regarding travels and general life updates, postcard from relatives, Christmas card, correspondence to friends regarding Switzerland in WW2, their engagement in the Jewish community, and good wishes for the High Holidays, official letter from the tax agency in Zurich.
  - Political cards and notes, 1969-2010 (Box 54, Folder 6, Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Stern, family, and friends, undated (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Stern family: publications, 1968, 2003-2010 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Stern family: Thommy Kramer thesis, 1993 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Claude Stern interview with Arthur, 1994 (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Grandchildren bar/bat mitzvah, 1997-2009 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - 75th birthday party Edith and Arthur, 2000 August (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - Family genealogy, 2003 (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - Passover in the Dob utca, 2010 (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Arthur Stern biographies and resumes, 1973-2008 (Box 56, Folder 2)
  - Book orders, 1969 (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - Notes on Israel, 1999-2000 (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Notes, 2003, 2007, most undated (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Bibliographies/booklists, 2002 (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - Letters to editors, 1979-2006 (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Jerusalem Post article, 2003 January (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Journal op-ed by Arthur Stern, 2008 (Box 56, Folder 9)
  - Address lists, undated (Box 56, Folders 10-11)
  - The Barbarians Before the Gate pre-print, 2000 (Box 56, Folder 12)
  - Notes and correspondence: whisky market, 1962-1974 (Box 57, Folders 1-3)
    German materials include: business correspondence between Leon and Arthur Stern regarding issues surrounding their whiskey investments, financial concerns, Arthur’s desire to divest due to losses, tax concerns, real estate, devaluation of the British pound, stock investments, brief discussion of German reparations, the overproduction of whiskey, insurance policies for whiskey investments, and negotiations with whiskey brokers and related firms in both Britain and Switzerland, contract with Stersa AG for purchase and subsequent sale of whiskey, Bank Koschland & Hepner AG reports on the whiskey market, production, prices, investment strategies, and about patterns of consumption in different countries.
  - Accident in Israel, 1975 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Personal travel, 1976-2005 (Box 58, Folders 1-2, Box 57, Folders 5-6)
  - Class action lawsuit, 2009-2010 (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - Media: Stern computer files, 2005, 2013 (Box 58, Folder 4)
    Contains two CD-Rs and one USB drive. Both CD-R's labelled: "Arthur's Machine 8/12/05 My Documents E-mail addresses Recovered emails 8/31/05" USB with email explaining contents: outlook files, personal financial information, correspondence
  - Artwork and ephemera, undated (Box 72)
  - Media: family photos and videos and file backups, 1988-2012 (Box 39)
    Contains 8 DVD-Rs, 2 CD-Rs, 6 CD-RWs, 6 flexidiscs. Includes file backups, family photos, granddaughter bat mitzvah video
- Series 4: Holocaust Restitution, 1938-2013
  The Holocaust Restitution subseries includes family correspondence related to restitution claims, legal correspondence related to those claims, and related official documents concerning real estate, finance, and family history. Much of this correspondence and related documentation is in German and Hungarian. It also includes Holocaust testimonials, oral history transcripts, and correspondence and media articles related to the Kasztner transport and Killing Kasztner, the documentary film made about the controversy. Additionally, it includes printed materials and related correspondence from organizations dedicated to assisting Holocaust survivors, including the California Humanitarian Foundation for Holocaust Survivors, for which Stern served as chairman.
  - Hungarian bank documents, 1938, 1961 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    German materials include: declaration in lieu of oath regarding financial worth and reparations claims.
  - Insurance and property claims, 1997-1998 (Box 59, Folders 2-3)
    German materials include: documents and correspondence pertaining to inheritance and property claims in Germany, petition for certificate of inheritance for heirs (Robert and Arthur) of Bertha Stern whose parents (Mechel and Feige Frankfurter) owned property in Germany, documents pertaining to heirs of Bertha and her siblings.
  - Hungarian restitution, 1991-1998 (Box 59, Folders 4-7)
    Folders 1-2 of 4: documents, correspondence, and questionnaire pertaining to inheritance and establishing Arthur and Robert as heirs to their mother, also Lilly (Livia) Frankfurter to Bernard Frankfurter, and other siblings.
    Folders 3-4 of 4: legal declaration and other documents pertaining to parent’s war experience and Hungarian restitution claims.
  - Berlin property claims, 1992-1999 (Box 60, Folders 1-4)
    Folders 1-2 of 4: correspondence and legal agreements related to 14 inherited properties in Berlin.
    Folders 3-4 of 4: correspondence with lawyers and relevant legal forms pertaining to property restitution and inheritance in Berlin, correspondence between lawyers and heirs in the 1950s pertaining to restitution and their statements regarding the forced sale of properties in Berlin during the Nazi period, form from Lilly Frankfurter relinquishing her claims, copies of official documents from forced sale of a property in the 1930s.
  - East Germany property restitution, 1992-1999 (Box 60, Folders 5-6)
    German materials include: correspondence with lawyers and legal documents related to property restitution claims in Berlin, legal proceedings regarding the return of certain properties – particularly Libauerstrasse 5, and correspondence between Stern’s lawyer and the Jewish Material Claims against Germany.
  - Restitution, 1995-2009 (Box 61, Folders 1-2)
    German materials include: correspondence with German officials and official forms pertaining to Arthur and Robert Stern claiming father Leon Stern’s restitution in Germany, correspondence about and claim against Germany calling for accurate pay out of interest on a property.
  - Property restitution, 1999-2004 (Box 61, Folders 3-4)
    German materials include: correspondence with lawyer and official German offices pertaining to property restitution and sale of certain properties in Berlin, bill for lawyer’s costs, property appraisal.
  - Restitution Claims, 1992-2003 (Box 61, Folders 5-6)
    German materials include: correspondence with lawyer and official documents pertaining to restitution, sale/auction of Berlin properties, and property claims, reports on the properties themselves, copy of report on Bergen-Belsen from survivors of Kasztner transport, official document on sale of Danzigerstrasse 51, correspondence between lawyer and conference on Jewish Material Claims against Germany regarding properties, official documents regarding inheritance and heirs.
  - Guide to Holocaust Reparations, 2000 (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - Kasztner, 1948, 2009-2010 (Box 62, Folders 1-2)
    Contains photocopy of document from 1948. German materials include: report on Bergen-Belsen and list of names in Kasztner Transport.
  - German restitution, 1956-1962 (Box 62, Folder 3)
    German materials include: legal documents, claims, and correspondence pertaining to reparations and restitution, especially regarding payments for health problems caused by experience in the Holocaust. Also pertaining to claims for Edith Stern.
  - Parents' German reparations, 1959-1963 (Box 62, Folder 4)
    German materials include: additional (rejected) reparations claims against the German government based on Bertha Stern’s health issues, rejection of Leon Stern’s claims, and Bertha Stern’s application for reparations based on her health, legal statements verifying Leon Stern’s character and position in Budapest at the time of German occupation.
  - Hungary partial compensation, 1959-1971 (Box 62, Folders 5-6)
    German materials include: reparations pertaining to Leon Stern and Joseph Stern, including correspondence with lawyers and official state offices in Germany (Stuttgart, Mainz) and legal forms. Also legal declarations regarding the basis and extent of the claims in Budapest and Germany, and statements from employees at the time of the German occupation of Hungary verifying Leon and Joseph Stern’s claims, medical documents and statements for Mrs. Bertha Stern-Frankfurter and Leon Stern to prove health damage done during Holocaust.
  - "An Interview with Arthur Stern", 1993 (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - Testimony and restitution reports, 1998-2007 (Box 63, Folders 1-2)
  - Holocaust: Bulgaria - Events in Los Angeles, 1990-2011 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Holocaust: Budapest/Hungarian, 1988-2008 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Switzerland/Swiss Consul General, 1998-1999 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    German materials include: correspondence pertaining to the role of Switzerland during the Second World War and thanking Stern for his efforts in the research, and his engagement in its support.
  - Holocaust-related clippings, 1998-2000 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Holocaust memorials/monuments, 1994, 1996 (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Holocaust: re: speaking engagements, 1997, 2003, 2004, 2010, 2012 (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - Holocaust oral history general, 1987, 1996 (Box 63, Folder 9)
  - Holocaust oral history, 2011 (Box 63, Folder 10)
  - Testimony: Mendel Max Rozmaryn, 2009 (Box 63, Folder 11)
  - Holocaust restitution, 1993-1997 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - California Holocaust Insurance Settlement Alliance, 1999-2002 (Box 64, Folders 2-3)
  - Association of Holocaust Survivors from the Former USSR, 1994-1997 (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - Jewish Council for Public Affairs materials, 1998-2000 (Box 64, Folder 5)
  - California Humanitarian Foundation for Holocaust Survivors, 2001-2006 (Box 65, Folders 1-5, Box 64, Folder 6)
  - Media: Oral histories and Holocaust-related films, 1996, 2011, 2013 (Box 39)
    Contains 4 DVD-Rs. Title list: "Survivors of the Shoah Visual History Foundation Interview 12494 1996 Arthur Stern", "Shoah: Edith Stern Interview 1996", Killing Kasztner (2008), The Empty Boxcars: a film by Ed Gaffney.
- Series 5: Community Involvement, 1966-2012
  The Community Involvement series includes correspondence and printed matter pertaining to the many community organizations with which Arthur Stern was involved, such as Americans for Peace Now, the California Israel Chamber of Commerce, and the Progressive Jewish Alliance. The files labelled “Jewish” include materials from a variety of Jewish organizations. The series also includes notes and correspondence related to Israel and politics in the Middle East, as well as correspondence related to Stern’s philanthropic activity.
  Contents are arranged by organization.
  - Correspondence: Seaver Science Library (USC) and Syracuse Library gifts, 1968-1988 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Publication Society, 1969-2005 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: community activity, 1969-2007 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Philanthropy, 1971-2012 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Anti-Defamation League Dinner Committee, 1986 April (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - Anti-Defamation League dinner - Torrance Marriott Hotel, 1986 June (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - New Israel Fund, 1990-1995 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - Arab/Jewish Speaker's Bureau, 1994 (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1994-1998 (Box 66, Folders 9-10)
  - Americans for Peace Now, 1994-2012 (Box 67, Folders 1-2, Box 66, Folder 11)
  - Jewish learning, 1996-2010 (Box 67, Folders 3)
  - Muslim/Jewish dialogue group, 1998-2001 (Box 67, Folders 4-5)
  - Progressive Jewish Alliance, 1999-2003 (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - Labor Zionist Alliance, 2000-2001 (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Tzedek Award, 2001, 2005, 2006 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - B'tselem, 2002-2011 (Box 68, Folders 2-4)
  - Bureau of Jewish Education, 2004-2006 (Box 68, Folders 5-6)
  - Association for Civil Rights in Israel, 2006-2011 (Box 69, Folder 1, Box 68, Folder 7)
  - Mt. Rushmore Institute, 2007 (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - "Fighter for Justice" article on Arthur Stern community involvement, 2010 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - Jewish: correspondence and printed materials, 1969-2012 (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - Jewish: reports, publications, and awards, 1969-2012 (Box 69, Folder 5)
  - Jewish: correspondence, printed materials, and events, 1969-2012 (Box 69, Folder 6)
  - Jewish: correspondence and reports, 1969-2012 (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - Jewish: correspondence and news clippings, 1969-2012 (Box 69, Folder 8)
  - Synagogue Beth Jacobs, 1968-1993 (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - Middle East politics clippings, 1981-2010 (Box 70, Folders 2-3)
    German materials include: articles from Die Welt on the USA’s attempt to decrease tensions in the Middle East and avoid being drawn into a war, and article on the 40th anniversary of Hermann Goering’s order to begin Jewish transports to the east.
  - Maps of Israel, 1982-1997 (Box 70, Folder 4)
  - Shinar, 1991-1992 (Box 70, Folder 5)
  - Shinar/Israel economic development, 1991-1993 (Box 70, Folders 6-7)
  - California Israel Chamber of Commerce, 1996-1998 (Box 70, Folder 8)
  - Jewish newspapers/magazines, 2003-2012 (Box 71)
  - Awards and recognition, 1966-2004 (Box 72)